Guide to the Martin Friedman Papers ALBA.218
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Martin Friedman Papers
1931-1966, (Bulk 1937-1938)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Friedman, Martin, 1914-1966
ALBA.218
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Martin Friedman (1914-1966) fought with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War and worked as a union organizer with the International Association of Machinists for over 25 years. This collection consists chiefly of weekly letters written by Friedman from Spain to his family in New York from 1937 through 1938. The collection also contains printed matter, artifacts and ephemera documenting Friedman’s time in Spain and his affiliation with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade following his return to New York.
Provenance
The Martin Friedman Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in June 2004 by his son Neil Friedman and daughter-in-law Ellen Bogolub.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Martin Friedman was born into a working-class family in Trenton, New Jersey on November 24, 1914 to Morris and Rose Friedman. He came of age during the Depression in the Bronx, and was raised by his older sister Zelda after his mother's death. Following his graduation from a vocational high school in 1930, Friedman attended the Baron de Hirsch Trade School in New York, trained as a machinist, and found work in Pennsylvania and New York in machine shops and metal works. He became a member of the International Association of Machinists (IAM) and from 1932 to 1935 was a volunteer in New York's 258th Field Artillery Unit of the United States National Guard. In February 1936, he joined the American League against War and Fascism and served as the Secretary of the Tremont Branch in the Bronx. Through his older sister Zelda and her husband Nat Baral, Friedman became active in the Communist Party and in November 1937 formally became a party member.
Motivated by anti-fascist sentiments, Friedman traveled to Spain to fight with the International Brigades to aid the Republican Army. He sailed for France in February 1937 and then made his way to Spain where he was initially assigned to an artillery unit in a French battalion, and by March was made sergeant of an American heavy artillery unit. He served in this capacity on the battlefront until the withdrawal of foreign volunteers from Spain in October 1938. Before departing Spain he spent time in Valencia and later Barcelona before returning to New York on the Queen Mary in February 1939.
Upon his return he resumed working as a machinist, and became active with the IAM as a labor organizer and shop steward. At a Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade dance in early 1941, Friedman met, and soon after married, Anne Naginsky. The couple had twin boys, Neil and Robert. Ineligible for military service during WWII (a blow to the head during a violent strike action left his vision impaired), Friedman worked at Todd Shipyards in New Jersey. In the years following the war Friedman organized Hispanic workers at Berger Industries and initiated a successful program of English language classes. Throughout the 1940s and early 1950s, Friedman remained an active member of the Communist Party, working as an organizer and serving as an aide to chairman William Z. Foster; but in 1956, following the revelations of Stalinist atrocities, Friedman withdrew in disillusionment from the party. Beginning in 1962, Friedman applied and was admitted to Queens College where he pursued studies in history and politics. Martin Friedman died in 1966 following a heart attack. He was 52 years old.
Scope and Content Note
Series I. Correspondence, 1937-1939; 1966. This series consists chiefly of letters written by Friedman from Spain to his sister Zelda, brother-in-law Nat, his father Morris, and friends Mary and Ben, who shared a Jackson Heights apartment with his family. Full of warmth and humor, Friedman's weekly letters home cover the period from his arrival in Spain in February 1937 to his demobilization in January 1939. These letters offer keenly observed accounts of the ravages of war, the quotidian existence of combat volunteers, the political and social conditions in Spain, and the beauty of the architecture and rural landscape. Also included are references to the Friedman family's fundraising activities in New York, extended commentary on the "Daily Worker," and declarations of Friedman's commitment to the Republican cause. Of particular note is a description of cooperative farming and land distribution in Catalonia (4/14/1937); a letter that details the plight of orphans and refugees (5/7/1937); and a Christmas greeting from Friedman's Spanish comrades at the front written on the back of a pre-printed International Brigade card (12/25/1937).
In addition this series includes a few letters written by fellow volunteers Arthur Goldberg (a.k.a. Gorgan) and Keith Harry Hubbard to Zelda and Nat. Goldberg served in Spain as an ambulance driver and was killed in April 1938. Hubbard, who signs his letters "Duke," served in the artillery unit with Friedman. A 1966 condolence letter from Moe Fishman, in his capacity as Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Secretary, to Friedman's widow Anne and a February 1939 (misdated 1938) telegram from Zelda received by Martin onboard the Queen Mary can also be found here.
Series II. Subject Files, 1931-1944. This series includes Friedman’s carnet militaire from Spain, his VALB membership card, and Spanish vocabulary sheets that he carried with him in Spain. Also here are Spanish political party, International Brigade and Socorro Rojo postcards; annotated copies of the International Brigade publication, The Volunteer for Liberty; and four published graphic works of Spanish Civil War-era prints and photographs. Of particular note are three 1937 pen-and-ink drawings by K. H. Hubbard satirizing life at the front and in the camps, and Friedman’s well-worn International Brigade signet ring with circular inscription in Spanish reading, "International Volunteers for Liberty." [Note: This ring is physically housed with the processed artifacts from the ALBA collections. Consult staff.]
Arrangement
Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically. Series II is arranged alphabetically.
Organized into 2 series:
Missing Title
I. Correspondence, 1937-1939; 1966.
II. Subject Files, 1931-1944.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Two photographs were separated from the Martin Friedman manuscript materials in the course of processing and have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Foreign public opinion.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Children.; Drawings (visual works); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Correspondence.; Graphic arts; Spain.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works.; Personal papers.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Periodicals.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Goldberg, Arthur J.; Friedman, Martin, 1914-1966; International Red Aid; Fishman, Moses (Moe), 1916-; Daily Worker (New York); Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Communist Party of the United States of America; Hubbard, Keith Harry.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1936-1966 [Bulk, 1936-1939]
  - Correspondence: Fishman, Moe, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Friedman, Martin, Feb 1937-May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Friedman, Martin, Jun 1937-Aug 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Friedman, Martin, Sep 1937-Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Friedman, Martin, Jan 1938-May 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Friedman, Martin, Jun 1938-Aug 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Friedman, Martin, Sep 1938-Jan 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Friedman, Martin: Fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Friedman Baral, Zelda, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Goldberg, Arthur (a.k.a. Quentin Arthur Gorgan), Dec 1937-Mar 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Hubbard, Keith Harry ("Duke"), Jan 1938-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1931-
  - Carnet Militaire, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Graphic Works: Atila en Galicia: Estampa por Castelao, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Graphic Works: Estampas de la Revolucion Espanola, 19 Julio de 1936(drawings by Sim), ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Graphic Works: Molne, Spanish Civil War, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Graphic Works: Spain ( Photo History Magazine publication), Apr 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Graphic Works: Twelve Dibujo (drawings by Martinez de Leon), ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hubbard, Keith Harry: Pen-and-Ink Drawings, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Brigade Signet Ring, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Leaflet: "Fifteenth Brigade: One Year of Battle", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pamphlet: Open Letter from the Spanish Communist Party (missing cover), in Spanish, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Postcards: International Brigade and Spanish Political Parties, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Socorro Rojo: Fundraising Stamps and Postcards, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Spanish Currency, 1931-1936 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Christmas Ball Fundraising Tickets, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Membership Card, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Vocabulary Sheets, Spanish/English, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Volunteer for Liberty, (some with annotations by Friedman), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)